Animation Number 1
What happened? Chapter 52? It basically doubled in one evening!
（羽川(はねかわ)）
何があった？
〝０５２〞って！
Animation Number 1
Animation Number 2
ひと晩で
ダブルスコア的に
Animation Number 2
章が飛んでる！
What kind of adventure would you have to go on
Animation Number 3
to skip 25 chapters?!
Skipping to this point, even I think it's a bit unnatural.
ここに至れば 私だって
さすがに不自然に思う
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I smell dirt.
土の匂い
Animation Number 8
I checked my feet.
寝ている間に 屋外に出た？
Did I go outside while I was asleep?
Animation Number 8
I didn't find anything on the soles.
Like a sleepwalker?
夢遊病者のように？
Animation Number 8
My feet are 23.5 cm
Animation Number 9
Quite beautiful.
But its position's different today.
でも 昨日と位置がズレている
Animation Number 11
By about three millimeters.
Which means...
ということは
When they say a criminal's proof remains under their fingernails, they weren't joking.
犯罪者の証拠は
爪の隙間に残るって言うけれど
シャレにならないな
Here it is. Definitive proof.
あった　決定的証拠
I see. So I'm turning into the Meddlecat again.
そっか
私 また なってるんだ 障(さわ)り猫(ねこ)
Into Black Hanekawa.
ブラック羽川に
Tsubasa Tiger          Part Four
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Good, it's not there. They're not growing yet.
（羽川）
大丈夫　生えてない
まだ 生えてない
It looks like a lot of things are different from the last two times.
いろいろと 前のとき
その前のときとは 違うみたいね
Since I had no omens and didn't have to rely on Araragi-kun to change me back,
前兆としての頭痛もないし
阿良々木(あららぎ)くんが不在なのに
こうして
元に戻れているところをみると
am I getting used to turning into Black Hanekawa?
ブラック羽川に なり慣れてきた
ということなのかな
But I can kind of imagine the reason why I turned into Black Hanekawa again.
でも どうして 私が
また ブラック羽川に
なったのかっていうのは
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
想像がつくよね
It's not relieving stress again by thrashing around.
また ストレスを発散するために
暴れているとかじゃないよね
If that were so, there'd probably be more noticeable signs.
それだったら もっと派手に
痕跡が残っていそうなものだし
What a bind.
まいったな
Is Black Hanekawa-chan going to handle this stress too?
このストレスも
ブラック羽川ちゃんは
引き受けてくれるのかしらん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Hanekawa-san.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（月火(つきひ)）羽川さ〜ん
（ノック）
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Are you awake? If not, wake up!
（月火）起きてる？
起きてなかったら 起きて
It's breakfast time! It's a rule in the Araragi household for all of us to eat breakfast together.
ご飯の時間だよ
阿良々木家では
朝ご飯は みんなで
一緒に食べる決まりなんだよ
Got it. Don't worry. I'm awake, so I'll be right there.
（羽川）うん 分かった
大丈夫 起きてるから
すぐ行くね
Okay.
（月火）は〜い
（階段を下りる足音）
Araragi-kun talks of his little sisters waking him every morning as if it were a nuisance.
（羽川）
阿良々木くんは
毎朝 妹さんたちから
起こされることを
随分と迷惑みたいに
言っていたけれど
こんな かわいらしい起こし方の
一体 どこが迷惑なんだろう？
But how's such a cute way to wake someone a nuisance?
Animation Number 48
What's wrong with him?
The way Araragi explains it,
Animation Number 48
one would be led to believe he's getting assulted in his sleep with a crowbar.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Animation Number 48
Holding contact lenses in one of my hands, I left Araragi's room.
Meow.
Animation Number 49
I'm heading out now.
いってきます
Hanekawa-chan.
（阿良々木の母）羽川ちゃん
Animation Number 51
Koyomi's mother
I don't know about your household's circumstances, and for now, I don't plan on asking.
君の家庭に
どういう事情があるのか知らないし
今のところ
聞こうとも思わないけれど
But don't consider being apart from your parents
今 こうして 両親の元を離れて
私たちの家から
“いってきます”を言う状態が
and saying "I'm heading out now" from our house as normal.
正常だとは思わないでね
We can entertain you as our guest, but we can't become your family.
私たちは 君を
もてなしてあげることは
できるけれど
君の家族に
なってあげられるわけじゃないんだ
Even if Karen and Tsukihi look up to you as an older sister.
火憐(かれん)や月火が いくら君を
姉のように慕っていたとしても
Ah, don't get me wrong. It's not that it's any trouble.
あ… 誤解しないでね
迷惑ってことじゃないんだよ
Karen and Tsukihi are happy, and I want to treat you well as a guest because you're Koyomi's friend.
火憐と月火も喜んでるし
暦(こよみ)の友達である羽川ちゃんには
できる限り よくしてあげたいし
Reference
I also heard it was thanks to you that Koyomi put more effort into studying.
暦が勉強に
精を出すようになったのも
Physics
聞けば 君のおかげだっていうしね
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That isn't the case.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（羽川）
そんなことはないです
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I'm sorry. I've worried you in a strange way.
すみません
なんか 変な心配を
かけてしまったみたいで
But my family circumstances aren't that big a deal.
でも 私の家庭の事情なんて
そんな大したことはないんです
There's just a little bit of a falling out. That's all...
ちょっと不仲というか
それだけのことで…
The mere fact there's a falling out between parent and child sounds like child abuse.
（阿良々木の母）
親が子供と仲が悪いというのはね
もう それだけで
虐待みたいなものなんだよ
Family is something you don't need but should be happy to have.
家族は いなきゃいけない
ものじゃないけれど
いたら うれしいもので
あるべきなんだ
That's what I think. As a mother.
私は そう思うよ
母親としては
As a mother...
母親として…
Hanekawa-chan, people can run from things they don't like all they want.
（阿良々木の母）羽川ちゃん
人は嫌なことがあったら
どんどん逃げていいんだけれど
But if they're just averting their eyes, they're not running.
目をそらしているだけじゃ
逃げたことには ならないんだよ
Animation Number 79
Words of a mother
As long as you think the current situation's okay, no one can help.
君が 現状をよしとしている限り
外からは
手出しができないんだから
For starters, I think that's about where you need to "head out" from.
まずは その辺りから
いってくれば
いいんじゃないかな？
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Just averting your eyes isn't running away, huh?
（羽川）
目をそらしているだけじゃ
逃げたことにはならない… か
Those are connotative words.
含蓄のある言葉だな
Animation Number 91
I came face-to-face
with a scene that made me want to avert my eyes.
Um...
えっと
Animation Number 92
A nasty-looking golden eye captures me.
Animation Number 100
We made eye contact.
Oh, hey, you.
ああ ああ お前
Um, what was it?
えっと 何だったっけ？
You're that girl I totally almost killed that time, right?
こないだ 俺に
ぶっ殺されかけたヤツだよな
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Totally makes me laugh.
超ウケる
Hello. It's been a while, Episode-san.
どうも お久しぶりです
エピソードさん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I heard you went back to your home country right after that incident, so why are you back, Episode-san?
あれから あなたは すぐに
故国に帰ったという話でしたけれど
どうして また
この町に来たんですか？
エピソードさん
Totally makes me laugh. Don't "Episode-san" me.
超ウケる
“エピソードさん”とか
言ってんじゃねえよ
I'm not old enough for that "-san" speak and not titled enough for formal speaking.
俺は そんな
さん付けされるような年じゃねえし
丁寧語を使われるような
立場でもねえ
Even though you're only half-vampire, your life span is pretty long, right?
（羽川）
え？　でも ハーフとはいえ
ヴァンパイアだし
寿命は それなりに長いはずでは？
A long life span doesn't make me old, right? Totally makes me laugh!
（エピソード）
寿命が長いからって
年寄りだとは限らねえだろ
超ウケる
This is actually a secret, but I'm so amused I'll tell you. Actually, you're a lot older than I am.
本当は ないしょなんだが
面白(おもしれ)えから教えてやるけど
実は 俺よりも あんたのほうが
よっぽど年上なんだぜ
Because right now, I'm six years old.
俺は 今日この時点じゃ
６歳なんだからよ
Six?
６歳？
Animation Number 115
I couldn't help it, but I was obviously surprised.
Well, just shows you not to judge a person by how they look. Though I'm not a human.
（エピソード）
まっ 人を見かけで
判断するなってことさ
俺は人じゃねえけどな
So will you answer my question regarding what brought you back to this town?
（羽川）
で なんで この町に
再び やって来たのか
っていう質問には
私は 答えてもらえるのかな？
You're really persistent about that, huh?
（エピソード）
あ？　やけに こだわるじゃねえか
Well, I owe you, so I'd like to answer you.
まあ お前には貸しがあるからな
答えてやりてえとこなんだけど
Animation Number 120
Looks like trying to kill me
is something he at least considers a debt.
But I still don't know why I'm back in this town myself.
けど 俺も 自分が何のために
この町に来たのかは
まだ分かんねえんだわ
I got called in and arrived this morning on a red-eye bus.
いきなり呼び出されて
今朝 夜行バスで
到着したばっかでよ
A red-eye bus?
夜行バスって…
Are you a tourist?
Animation Number 121
（羽川）
妙に庶民派だ
Called in?
（羽川）“呼び出されて”って？
Of course. I'm basically a freelance vampire hunter. Not like Dramaturgie or Guillotine Cutter.
（エピソード）呼び出されもするさ
俺は 基本的にフリーの
ヴァンパイアハンターなんだから
ドラマツルギーや
ギロチンカッターとは違う
金払いさえよきゃ
誰にでも雇われる
If the cash reward's good, I'm for hire. I'm a mercenary for personal gain.
私情で動く傭兵(ようへい)さ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Hired without knowing the case?
（羽川）
用件も聞かずに雇われるの？
（エピソード）
前払いだったからな
They paid up front, and I also had reasons why I had to accept.
それに 引き受けなきゃなんねえ
事情もあった
I don't care about the case.
まあ 用件なんざ 何でもいいさ
Then could you be hired to go tiger hunting, too?
じゃあ ひょっとして
虎退治とかでも請け負うのかな？
Tiger hunting?
虎退治？
えっと… いや
Well, no, I'm a hunter specializing in vampires, so tigers and stuff are kinda...
俺は 吸血鬼専門の狩人だから
虎とかは ちょっと…
But, Hanekawa Tsubasa, was it? You've gotten like, really normal since we last met.
しかし お前 羽川翼(つばさ)だっけ？
なんか この前と比べて
すっげえ普通になっちまったな
I mean, just now,
だって さっきも この俺が
the "vision" I have as a vampire couldn't tell if you were the same person or not.
この俺のヴァンパイアの視力が
一瞬 お前なのかどうか
分かんなかった具合だしよ
Last time I got, kind of,
この前のお前から感じた
なんつうか
a dreadful feeling from you. It's gone without a trace now.
すごみ みたいなものが
きれいさっぱり消えうせてるぜ
No, not gone without a trace. More like it was cut off from you, leaving nothing behind.
消えうせてるというよりは
切り離されたかのように
何の痕跡もなく…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Animation Number 150
I got what he was trying to say.
But hold it right there.
Animation Number 150
This train of thought—
won't lead to anything good.
（エピソード）
おっ あいつだよ あいつ
It's her, it's her! The one who called me here without telling me about the case.
用件も言わずに
俺を呼び出しやがったヤツはよ
Well, when I heard she was an upperclassman to that Hawaiian-shirt Oshino Meme guy in college
いや なんでも 聞いてみれば
あの忍野(おしの)メメってアロハ野郎の
大学時代の先輩らしいんだけど
I had to accept this case because of my relationship with that guy.
だからこそ 縁もゆかりもある俺は
引き受けざるをえなかったわけだが
Animation Number 160
Hey, 'Sode. You were taking forever to come to the meeting place, so I came to pick you up.
（臥煙(がえん)）やあ ソード
いつまでたっても
待ち合わせ場所に来てくれないから
こちらから迎えに来たよ
And it seems you're in the middle of hitting on a girl. Sorry to interrupt.
すると どうやら
ナンパの最中だったようで
お邪魔をしてしまったのだったら
悪かった
ん？　おや そちらのお嬢さんは
Oh, is that girl there Hanekawa Tsubasa-san?
羽川翼さんかい？
あっ はい そうですけれど
Yes, that's me.
What a coincidence.
（臥煙）これは これは 偶然だな
I'm pleased I decided to move on a whim and got to meet you,
たまたま 私が気まぐれを起こし
自分から動いたおかげで
君に会えて うれしいよ
Tsubasa-chan.
翼ちゃん
I'm sure Meme didn't tell you, but I'm his senpai, a human named Gaen Izuko.
メメから聞いていないと思うけれど
私は 彼の先輩で
臥煙伊豆湖(いずこ)という人間だ
Gaen Izuko
He called me Gaen-senpai.
（臥煙）
彼からは 臥煙先輩と呼ばれていた
Don't say "hitting on." I was just relishing in old memories because I saw a familiar face.
（エピソード）
ナンパとか言うなよ 臥煙さん
俺は 懐かしい顔に会ったから
思い出話に
花を咲かせていただけだぜ
Well, that doesn't matter.
まあ どうでもいいのさ
そんなことは
If that talk of old memories is over, let's be on our way. Every second counts for us.
その思い出話とやらが
終わったのなら
行こうじゃないか
事は刻一刻と 一刻を争うんだ
おっつけ 余接(よつぎ)も来るだろうが
それを待ってもいられない
Yotsugi will follow us, but we can't wait.
Yotsugi? Who's that?
（エピソード）
余接？　誰だよ そりゃ
It doesn't matter for you.
誰でもいいんだ ソードにとっては
It does matter for certain people, like me.
そうでないヤツも
いるというだけで
例えば 私にとっては そうではない
いや 本当を言えば
No, to tell the truth, I wish either Meme or Deishu were here.
メメか泥舟(でいしゅう)の どちらかが
いてくれたらとは思うよ
But they're very much vagabonds. As for Yozuru, I don't want her here at all.
ただ あの２人は
どうにも風来坊だからね
ちなみに 余弦(よづる)には いてほしくない
ちっともだ
You really talk for yourself. Like you talk assuming the other side knows what you know.
ホント あんた 自分の都合でしか
しゃべらねえよな
自分の知ってることを
相手が知ってる前提で
しゃべるっつうかよ
Tsubasa-chan, if things were normal, I'd join in the chat with 'Sode.
（臥煙）翼ちゃん
本来ならば ソードと君との
おしゃべりに混ぜてもらって
なんなら大人として 君たち２人に
As an adult, I should probably even buy you two some juice at a vending machine.
自動販売機でジュースでも
おごってあげるのが
あるべき私なのだけれど
But it's like I said. Sorry, but I'm taking 'Sode.
今 話したような事情でね
悪いけど ソードは連れていくよ
Okay.
あ… はい
So I can't help you with the tiger problem you're carrying around right now.
だから 君が今 抱えている
虎の問題についても
You'll have to take care of that yourself somehow.
手伝ってあげるわけにはいかない
それは 自分１人で
なんとかしてくれ
Animation Number 189
Tiger— issues?
What's that weird look for?
ん？　何だい？　変な顔をして
虎のことを知っていた程度のことで
そんな驚くことはないだろう
Knowing about the tiger isn't so surprising.
There's nothing I don't know.
私に知らないことは ないんだよ
Nothing you don't know...
知らないことは… ない
Yeah.
Animation Number 194
She said it.
I know everything.
私は 何でも知っている
Animation Number 197
So confidently.
As if she had total control of everything in this story.
Animation Number 197
She said.
Well, I'm sure you'll be facing the tiger either today or tomorrow.
まあ 君は きっと今日明日中に
その虎と
向き合うことになるのだろう
You'll face the one you're about to name the "History Tiger."
君自身が もうすぐ
Hyst
“苛虎(かこ)”と名付けることになる
Hysteria Tiger
The aberration with strength unparalleled in history.
その古今無比に強力な怪異とね
But nobody can help you with that. Nobody can rescue you.
だけど それは 誰にも手伝えない
君は 誰にも助けてもらえない
Because it's a problem you yourself have.
なぜなら それは
君自身の問題なのだから
That's not my problem, and of course it's not the problem of the boy you're in love with.
それは 私の問題ではないし
もちろん 君が恋する男の子の
問題でもない
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Animation Number 210
The boy I'm in love with?
I'm talking about Araragi Koyomi-kun. You really didn't know?
阿良々木暦くんだよ
まさか 知らないのかい？
You really don't know anything, Tsubasa-chan. You don't even know that you don't know anything.
君は何にも知らないんだね
翼ちゃん
自分が何も知らない
ということさえ 知らない
無知の知ならぬ
It's not wisdom to realize one's ignorance. It's ignorance.
無知の無知
ということかな？
Animation Number 216
It's not wisdom to realize one's ignorance.
アッハ！
Saying "muchi" so much makes it sound naughty, like the word for a voluptuous body.
無知の無知なんて言うと
なんだか
ムッチムッチの
豊満ボディーみたいで
いやらしいよね
I do feel jealous since I'm the slender type.
私は痩せ形だから 羨ましいものだ
Though it's probably better to not know of one's ignorance.
とはいえ 無知の知なんて
知らないほうが
いいんだろうけれどね
Nothing's worse than the truth you're an idiot, like the lament of the scarecrow without a brain.
“自分がバカだって事実ほど
たまらないものはない”と
脳を持たない かかしも
嘆いていたことだし
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
You... What do you know about me?
あなたは…
あなたは 私の何を
知っているんですか？
I know everything. As I said, I know everything.
何でも知っているよ
だからね 私は何でも知っている
I know that you don't know anything, but that's nothing to be ashamed of.
君が何も知らないことも
私は知っている
しかし それは
恥じるべきことじゃないよ
世の中の人間ってヤツは
みんな 何も知らないんだから
All humans in this world don't know anything. They unwittingly live using every trick in the book.
知らず知らずのうちに
だましだまし生きているんだ
You're no exception. You're not special.
君は例外じゃない
君は特別じゃない
Animation Number 229
Said Gaen.
Not an exception, not special.
（羽川）
例外じゃなく 特別じゃない
Animation Number 230
As if she were looking down on me.
You like when people say that.
そう言われると うれしいんだろ？
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I know that.
知っているよ
Of course, I know that the cram-school ruins,
もちろん 昨日の夜
メメを含む君たちにとっては
思い出の場所とも言うべき
a location you guys, including Meme, look back on with fond memories, burned down last night.
あの学習塾跡の廃虚が
燃えてしまったことだって
私は ちゃんと知っているさ
Oh, this was also information you weren't aware of,
ああ これもまた
まだ君が知らない情報だったっけ？
Tsubasa-chan, who doesn't know everything.
何でもは知らない翼ちゃん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Animation Number 240
On my way back from school. No, I can't say that.
（羽川）
学校からの帰り道
いや これは帰り道とは言えない
Because I was planning a detour, not heading straight to the Araragi house.
私は 阿良々木家に直接 帰らず
寄り道をするつもりでいるのだから
That's right. I know that the fire was something that has nothing to do with Araragi-kun or Kanbaru-san.
そう 私は知っている
その火事が
阿良々木くんや神原(かんばる)さんとは
何の関係もなく
起きたものであることを
I don't know, but the me that isn't me knows.
（羽川）
私は知らないけれど
私じゃない私が 知っている
I probably know because I saw it last night as Black Hanekawa.
Mitsüi Logistics
多分 昨夜
私がブラック羽川になったときに
見て 知っている
So like Gaen-san said, this is my own problem.
だから 臥煙さんの言うとおり
これは 私の事件だ
Animation Number 284
Time passes
Municipal Library
Gaen-san said the "History Tiger", didn't she?
（羽川）
苛虎って言ったっけ 臥煙さんは
Animation Number 288
Occult
No books listed an aberration or transformed monster named the "History Tiger".
（羽川）
苛虎なる怪異 妖怪変化(へんげ)について
記述してある書籍は なかった
New title
ん？　ちょっと待って
Wait a minute.
New title
New releases?
New releases
新刊か
Animation Number 297
New releases—
New releases.
Animation Number 297
New releases—
（羽川）
新刊 新種…
Animation Number 297
New releases—
New variety
New variety.
Animation Number 297
New variety
Animation Number 298
I suddenly came up with something—
Animation Number 297
No no, it's not right to say I came up with it.
If this much research can't catch one hint,
Animation Number 297
No no, it's not right to say I came up with it.
これだけ調べても ヒントさえ
つかめないっていうのなら
Animation Number 297
No no, it's not right to say I came up with it.
Because Gaen said it right from the start.
what if that tiger is a new type of aberration just like Black Hanekawa?
Animation Number 297
That this would be an aberration I'd name personally.
ブラック羽川が そうだったように
あの虎が
新種の怪異なんだとしたら…
Animation Number 300
Namishiro Park
The hysteria of tyrants causes more harm than tigers.
Animation Number 301
So if Hysteria Tiger isn't short for "The hysteria of tyrants causes more damage than tigers,"
（羽川）
だから 苛虎っていうのは単純に
“苛政は虎よりも猛(たけ)し”を略して
苛虎なんじゃなくって
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I'd think it's a tiger worse than a tyrant. A tiger that surpasses all tigers in history.
“苛政よりもマシじゃない虎”
って意味での
虎を超える虎としての苛虎
なんじゃないかなって思うんだけど
What do you think?
どうかな？
I'm not sure.
（戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)）どうかしらね
It feels like you're being guided as this Gaen lady wishes.
（戦場ヶ原）
なんだか いいように
誘導されているって気もするけれど
その臥煙って人に
From your story, it's not you who named it, no matter how I think about it, she did.
話だけ聞いていると
羽川さんが名付けたんじゃなくって
どう考えても その人が
名付けているわけでしょ？
Well, that's true.
（羽川）
うん　まあ そうなんだけど
By the way, I think she's related to Kanbaru.
（電話:戦場ヶ原）
ちなみに 多分その人 神原の何かよ
I believe her mother's maiden name was Gaen. Kanbaru herself said she used to be Gaen Suruga.
（戦場ヶ原）
確か 神原の母方の姓が
臥煙だったはずよ
神原自身 昔は臥煙駿河(するが)って
名前だったって
It's a bit too unique to be a coincidence, a distant relative, or not be related.
無関係とか 偶然とか
遠い親戚とか言うには
ちょっと
あざとすぎる気はするわね
You're right.
（羽川）そうだね
Animation Number 320
Gaen Izuko's — line
Yes. I know everything.
Animation Number 320
Gaen Izuko's — line
（臥煙）
ああ　私は 何でも知っている
Animation Number 320
Gaen Izuko's — line
"History Tiger", was it?
苛虎だっけ？
Animation Number 322
Assuming
Let's say you were brave and trusted Gaen-san.
Animation Number 322
Assuming
仮に 勇気を出して
その臥煙さんを信用してみるとして
If someone said "History," I'd associate it with "the past."
私的には“苛虎”と言われれば
普通に パストの“過去”を
連想するけれどね
As in "former"?
（羽川）昔って意味？
It fits better than writing it with "fire" and "tiger." Combined with a traumatic meaning.
火の虎と書いて火虎とするよりは
それっぽいでしょ？
トラウマ的な意味合いも
合わせて言えば
Trauma?
トラウマ？
Oh no, that sounds like a pun.
あら やだ
そっちもそっちで
ダジャレっぽくなっちゃったかしら
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
It's prone to happen.
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
ありがちよね
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
History and Hysteria, huh?
Animation Number 327
History— and Hysteria, huh?
（羽川）
過去と 苛虎か…
But naming aside, doesn't that aberration seem fairly dangerous?
（戦場ヶ原）
でも ネーミングは ともかくとして
それって かなり実際的な危機を
伴っている怪異じゃないの？
That's right. Unlike my crab or Mayoi-chan's snail,
そう　私の蟹(かに)や
真宵(まよい)ちゃんの蝸牛(かたつむり)とは違って
it's like Kanbaru's left arm.
それこそ 神原の左腕にも似た…
What do you mean?
え？　どういうこと？
What do I mean?
どういうことって…
あなたに それが
There's no way you don't know.
分かっていないはずが
ないでしょうに
The ruins were burned down right after your house, right?
羽川さんの家と 学習塾が
こうして連続で
火災に遭ったわけでしょう？
Yes, that's right. There's no proof that links them to me meeting the tiger though.
（羽川）ええ そう
まあ それらと虎に遭ったこととを
関連づける証拠は
残念ながら 今のところ
ないんだけれど
It doesn't matter if there are any links there.
（戦場ヶ原）
そこに関連性があるかどうかは
どうでもいいのよ
There's a common thread to those two places besides the macroview that you knew them well.
ただ その２か所には
羽川さんにとって
よく知る場所という
マクロ的な共通点以外にも
もう１つ とてもミクロ的な
A microview, a common thread in a very short time span.
とても短期的な共通点も
あるでしょう？
（羽川）え？　だから それは
The fact they burned right after I saw the tiger that day.
私が あの日 虎を見た直後に
火災に遭っているっていう…
That's not it. I mean the places where you spent the night burned down one after another.
（戦場ヶ原）じゃなくて これは
あなたが 直前に寝床とした場所が
連続で燃えたということじゃない
So if this continues, my apartment and Araragi-kun's house
つまり このままだと
私のアパートや
阿良々木くんの家も 今晩あたり
will sadly be burned to a crisp tonight, no?
全焼の憂き目に遭っちゃう
ってことなんじゃなくて？
Animation Number 350
That's right. It's about time I settled this.
（羽川）
そうだ　もう けりをつけなければ
ならないのだ
This story about fires... about me...
火事にまつわる 私にまつわる
この物語に
Um, excuse me.
え〜っと おじゃまします
Welcome back, Tsubasa-san. You're pretty late. Where'd you go?
（火憐(かれん)）おかえり 翼さん
（火憐）
遅かったじゃ〜ん
どこ寄ってたの？
I was hanging out at the park for a bit.
ちょっと その辺の公園にね
寄ってたんだ
ふ〜ん
Any word from Araragi-kun?
阿良々木くんから 連絡あった？
Actually, no.
（火憐）それがねえんだよ
He can only debauch so much. I'll punt him hard when he's back.
あの兄ちゃん 放蕩(ほうとう)にも程があるぜ
帰ってきたら
蹴っ飛ばしてやるんだ
思いっきりな
Animation Number 360
It seems Araragi,
Well, who cares about a petty big brother.
まあ あんな
どうでもいい兄ちゃんのことは
Animation Number 360
even if he comes back safely, has a
predicament to overcome afterwards.
Animation Number 360
Not just one, but several.
どうでもいいんだ
I was waiting for you.
翼さん 待ってたんだぜ
Tsukihi-chan's back, so let's play. I already got some playing cards on the coffee table.
月火ちゃんも もう帰ってるから
何かゲームして遊ぼう
既に リビングのテーブルに
トランプを用意してあるんだ
Playing cards?
トランプ？
Animation Number 360
It's not, like, video games then.
Oh, I'm sorry, Karen-chan. I need to think-
あっ でも ごめんなさい
火憐ちゃん
私 部屋で考えたいことが…
Come on! Don't think you can resist...
（火憐）ほら 早く早く
私に 抵抗できると思うな！
Wai-! I got it! Let me take off my shoes!
ちょ… 分かった 分かった
だから 脱がせて　靴を脱がせて
I'll do it! I'll play cards!
する する　トランプするから〜！
Hurray!
（火憐）わ〜い！
Animation Number 379
Something to associate with "fire"? There's only one thing.
（火憐）
火という言葉から 連想するもの？
んなもん 決まってんじゃねえか
The hot heart beating in my chest. In a word, passion.
私の胸に宿る熱い心だよ
つまり ひと言で言えば
情熱ってことだ
（羽川）ふ〜ん　だったら
Then what do you associate with "flame"?
炎って言葉から連想するものは？
The hot passion is even hotter. In a word, justice.
（火憐）
熱い情熱が 更に熱いってことだ
ひと言で言えば 正義だな
（羽川）う〜ん なるほどね
Hmm, I see.
That's why you call yourselves the Fire Sisters?
だから 火憐ちゃんたちは
ファイヤーシスターズを
名乗っているの？
That's right! Fire Sisters means sisters of justice!
（火憐）そうだ
ファイヤーシスターズとは
つまり 正義姉妹ということなのさ
Actually, it's completely different.
（月火）
正確に言えば 全然 違うんだけどね
We're called the Fire Sisters simply because
私たちがファイヤーシスターズって
呼ばれてるのは 普通に
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
the kanji for "fire" is in our names.
２人とも名前に
“火”が入っているからだよ
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
By the way, I'd associate "fire" and "flame" with a heart in love.
ちなみに私は
火とか炎とかいう言葉からは
A heart in love.
恋心を連想するかな
恋心
White Scene
Animation Number 'none'
A heart in love, huh?
恋心ねえ…
Well, you might not know this,
ほら 羽川さんは
知らないかもしれないけれど
ファイヤーシスターズって
正義活動だけじゃなく
but we don't act just for justice. We also give romantic advice.
恋愛相談とかも受け付けてるから
（羽川）そうなの？
You do?
We even gave Onii-chan advice about his romance.
うん　お兄ちゃんの恋愛相談にも
乗ってあげたことが
あるくらいだよ
Araragi-kun?
え？　阿良々木くんの？
Animation Number 397
Really.
That kinda puts me off.
Come to think of it, there was something like that. Around May?
おお そういや
何かあったな そんなこと
５月ごろだっけか？
He asked a newbie question like, "What's it mean to be in love?"
好きって どういうことなのかとか
そんな青臭いことを
聞かれた気がするぜ
I see. So in other words, he sought advice from you two about Senjougahara-san?
（羽川）
へえ　それは つまり
戦場ヶ原さんのことで
火憐ちゃんや月火ちゃんに
相談したってことなのかな？
Animation Number 398
Why does this feel so unnatural?
Hmm... I don't know. We're talking about a while back.
ん〜 どうだったかな？
もう だいぶ前のことだから
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I've forgotten what he was talking about
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
お兄ちゃんが
どんなことを言ってたかなんて
忘れちゃったけれど
Lilac Scene
Animation Number 'none'
and how we answered.
私たちが 何て答えたかも
Anger has that "fire" feeling too, but that's more like what Karen-chan said about justice.
怒りも 火って感じだけれど
それは 火憐ちゃんが言うところの
正義に通ずるものだよね
For her, justice is anger.
Anger - Justice
火憐ちゃんにとっての正義って
怒りだから
That's right!
そうだ！
Anger's a flame and therefore justice!
つまり 怒りが炎で 正義なんだ
In any case, "passionate feelings" is the mutual understanding for me and Karen-chan.
（月火）
どちらにしても“熱い気持ち”って
理解をしていることになるのかな
私と火憐ちゃんは
Passionate feelings...
熱い気持ち…
What do you mean, "in any case," Tsukihi-chan? Passionate feelings equals justice.
いや どちらにしてもって何だよ
月火ちゃん
熱い気持ち
イコールで 正義だろうが
But your feelings towards Mizudori-kun aren't justice, but they're still passionate, right?
でもさあ 火憐ちゃん
火憐ちゃんの
瑞鳥(みずどり)くんに対する気持ちは
正義じゃないけど
熱い気持ちでしょ？
I guess so. Sorry. I was wrong.
ん〜 まあ そうだな
ごめん　私が間違ってたよ
Animation Number 411
It was an abnormal  meekness
Mizudori-kun?
（羽川）瑞鳥くんって？
（月火）火憐ちゃんの彼氏
Karen-chan's boyfriend.
Animation Number 414
Mizudori-kun
And my boyfriend's name is Rousokuzawa-kun.
ちなみに 私の彼氏は蝋燭沢(ろうそくざわ)くん
Animation Number 415
Rousokuzawa-kun
What? You both have boyfriends? I hadn't heard anything from Araragi-kun.
（羽川）え？　あれ？
２人とも 彼氏がいるの？
阿良々木くんから そんなの
聞いたことがないけれど
Oh, yeah. Those two don't exist inside his head.
（火憐）ああ 兄ちゃんの中では
その２人は
いないことになってるから
Animation Number 418
Sounds like Araragi-kun, all right.
So what are they like?
（羽川）ちなみに どんな人？
Just like our brother!
（火憐）兄ちゃんみたいなヤツ
（月火）お兄ちゃんみたいな人
These two really are...
（羽川）
この兄妹(きょうだい) やっぱ…
Animation Number 421
I regret asking.
It's a pain. I'd like it officially approved by our brother,
困ったもんなんだよな
なんとかして 兄ちゃんの公認を
得たいところなんだけど
but for some reason he refuses to meet either of them.
どうしてか 兄ちゃん
瑞鳥くんとも 蝋燭沢くんとも
会ってくれねえんだよな
Right. Yet he had the nerve to introduce Senjougahara-san to us. He's got some nerve.
（月火）そうだよねえ
そのくせ 自分は ちゃっかり
戦場ヶ原さんを
私たちに紹介するんだから
ちゃっかりしてるよ
Isn't that cute.
（羽川）
アハハ　かわいいもんじゃない
It boils down to him feeling like his cute little sisters are being taken from him.
どうしても こうしても
要するに 阿良々木くんは
かわいい妹を
取られたみたいな気持ちで
その２人に嫉妬してるって
だけでしょ？
So he's envious of those two. He's just being jealous.
やきもちを焼いているっていうのか
Being jealous?
（羽川）
やきもちを… 焼く？
Envy.
嫉妬… ああ そうだ
Oh, that's right.
That's another keyword associated with "fire" that might be the first one that comes to mind.
それも また
明らかに まず最初に
連想されてもいいくらいに
火に連なるキーワードじゃないか
Put another way, the fact they don't exist in Araragi-kun's mind means he's averting his eyes from the truth.
阿良々木くんの中で
いないことになっているというのは
言いかえれば 阿良々木くんが
真実から目をそらしている
ということであり
Animation Number 435
On just that one point, we're the same.
Just like me. Averting my eyes. Turning away from reality.
Animation Number 435
On just that one point, we're the same.
私と同じだ
Animation Number 435
On just that one point, we're the same.
目をそらし 現実から それている
Simply put, that's one of the strongest feelings humans have.
それが何に起因するのかと言えば
人の中で 最も強い感情の１つ
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
So strong it counts as one of the seven cardinal sins. Surely it's envy.
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
７つの大罪の１つにさえ数えられる
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
avarice
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
glu
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
lust
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
gluttony
envy
wrath
avarice
envy
正しく 嫉妬ではないか
So I'm jealous...
だから やきもちを 焼いている
Animation Number 442
（羽川）ハア…
Cutting away memory. Cutting away my heart.
（羽川）
記憶を切り離し 心を切り離す
It's easy to grasp if I think about my conversation with Episode-kun this morning.
今朝の通学路で エピソードくんと
話したときのことを思えば
分かりやすい
I thought I was trying to remember what happened during spring break, though I was slightly scared.
私は私で 私なりに
春休みのことを思い出しつつ
Reference
怖がりながら 彼と
立ち話をしたつもりだったけれど
But there couldn't have been a stranger sight.
ほかの誰かから見れば
あんな奇行はないだろう
I was chatting with someone who tried to kill me.
自分を殺そうとした相手と
私は歓談していたのだ
Could there be such an abnormal story?
そんな異常な話があるか？
I might not be able to see Araragi-kun again...
（羽川）
もう 会えないかもしれないな
阿良々木くん
This is what's called "marking" in the animal world.
（羽川）
これは 動物で言うところの
マーキングなのだ
I'm sure Araragi-kun will notice. Even if I never see him again.
きっと 阿良々木くんなら
気付くだろう
たとえ もう二度と会えなくっても
When he sleeps on this bed, maybe he'll remember me, even just a little.
このベッドで眠るとき
ちょっとくらいなら
私のことを思い出してくれると思う
Animation Number 463
Let's settle for that. That should be enough for me.
Well, that's enough.
（羽川）よし もういいや
ヤバい
Oh no, I should hurry.
Animation Number 465
I spent too long rolling about.
ちょっと急がないと
Animation Number 478
Visual confirmation
Delete
（連続する
シャッター音）
Animation Number 478
Delete
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Attachment
Sent
All right.
よし
This really may not be entirely necessary.
（羽川）
本当は これは必要のない
工程かもしれない
This might be pointless.
ムダなことを
しているのかもしれない
I don't have memories of being Black Hanekawa, but Black Hanekawa should have memories of me.
私には ブラック羽川としての
記憶はないけれど
Reference
ブラック羽川には 私としての
記憶があるはずなのだから
Yet still I, as only I can, want to share my feelings with the girl who is me, but separate from me.
それでも 私は あくまで私として
shinzou ni awasete hontou no kimochi o
I will convey my feelings my own way
私ではない
独立した私である彼女に
jibunrashiku saa hanasou
to match the excitement of my heart.
私の気持ちを伝えたかったのだ
To her, who took all my dark parts, my "black" parts, and carried them for me on her back,
これまで 私に代わって
私の暗い部分を 私の黒い部分を
全部 背負ってきてくれた彼女に
I want to show my appreciation and relay to her one last wish.
お礼の気持ちと
それから 最後のお願いを
heibon na kin’youbi ochikonda mainichi wa
It was a usual friday, even though I had
To Black Hanekawa.
伝えたかったのである
fuan to koukai no renzoku
felt so anxious and nervous before it.
sakusen o kangaete kono kimochi douyatte
I kept thinking of the battle plan
iou kana tte kyou mo owaru
of how I can I convey my feelings.
kimi no me ga oyoidara
Your eyes aren't focused on me
fuan de shouganainda yo
so it makes sense that I'm so anxious!
shittoshichau iya da iya da tte uzumaite
“Don't be jealous!” I tell myself.
tamaranainda
I can't help it!
HONTO wa ne zutto kimi to
You know, I just wanted it
futari dake gayokattanda
to be the two of us.
junsui na AI no KOTOBA
“My love is genuine”
warawanaide yo nee
So don't laugh, ok?
kitto mata sonna kimi o
But even if you do, I'm sure
akiramete yaru monka tte
I won't give up on you and will desperately
hisshi ni kotae o sagasu
search for my answer.
baka mitai da ne aa
I must look so stupid…
nee, me to me o awasetara
“Hey,” I say as our eyes meet,
kowagarazu ni hora hanashite miyou
I'll say it without fear.
jibun dake no kokoro o
My true feelings.
tameiki o tsuite saa RISETTO shiyou
Let me take a deep breath and start over.
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
Karen here!
（火憐）火憐だぜ！
（月火）月火だよ！
And Tsukihi!
I'm Tsukihi!
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
White Cat
（月火･火憐）
２人合わせて
“ファイヤーシスターズ”！
（月火）
クイズ予告編
Quiz Preview!
Let's investigate the arsonist case!
（火憐）
地獄編みたいに言うなよ
Don't make it sound like hell.
（月火）ジャンル“文学”
（火憐）無謀なことを
Genre time!
Where is this coming from...?
（月火）
ＳＦといえば
“少し不思議”の略ですが
The SF initials can be used for some strange things.
They mean "Science Fiction" right?
（火憐）
サイエンスフィクションだろ？
Let's play a game where we review some of those cases by changing the meaning of these initials.
I know nothing.
Hm...
It's no use.
（月火）
このイニシャリズムを
意味を変えずに略さず言うという
遊びをしましょう
題して“イニシャルシフト”！
面白いぞ
Let's call it: Initial Shift! It's gonna be fun.
Not sure if a game without Kendo can be considered fun.
（火憐）
面白いかな？
どういう遊びなのか
見当もつかないぜ
Cooperative People
are a Godsend.
Come here!
We'll tell you everything!
（月火）“少々 不可解”
（火憐）そういう遊びか！
"Obvious Mystery".
(Shoushou Fukakai)
What kind of game is that!?
"3.14% of ratios make you fluffy".
(San te ichi yon paasento no wariai de Fuwa fuwa shiteru)
（月火）
“3,14％の割合で ふわふわしてる”
（火憐）
割合が ふわふわしてねえだろ
厳密だろ
Ratios can't make you fluffy, ever.
Is the evil bully tiger headed to Gahara-san's house?
That's terrible!
"Somewhat Fantasy".
（月火）
“そこそこ ファンタジー”
So now it's Fantasy?
（火憐）
ファンタジーになってるぞ
"A bit strange" doesn't feel satisfactory, does it?
(Sukoshi Fushigi)
（月火）
少し不思議ってことは
大体 納得なんだよね
（火憐）
その発想に納得できない
I can't stand the way you think!
Next Time
Tsubasa Tiger Part 5
（火憐･月火）
次回「猫物語（白）」
Next Time! Nekomonogatari Shiro Episode 5!
第５話「つばさタイガー其ノ伍(そのご)」
Tsubasa Tiger, Part 5.
"Sister Fires".
Trying to pick a fight with Gahara-san
Just thinking about it is scary!
（月火）
“シスターファイヤーズ”
That is a weird transposition...
（火憐）
不思議な語感だ